Guide to the Clinton Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Clinton papers
1754-1879
OSB MSS 168
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.3
(41 boxes)
The Clinton Papers contain correspondence, letterbooks, financial papers and other material documenting aspects of the lives and military careers of Sir William Henry Clinton (1769-1846) and his brother Sir Henry Clinton (1771-1829). They include hundreds of letters from Henry to William Henry, many written from Spain during the Napoleonic Wars, as well as letters by other members of the Clinton family; journals kept by Sir Henry Clinton, the letterbooks of Sir William Henry Clinton, and account books kept by both brothers; bills and receipts; and family papers
Clinton family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by James Marshall Osborn from Hodgson's, 1958; gift of James Marshall Osborn, 1965.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sir William Henry Clinton, 1769-1846
Sir William Henry Clinton was the eldest son of General Sir Henry Clinton (1730-1795), who commanded the British forces in North America during the Revolutionary War. William Henry joined the British Army in 1784 and was swiftly promoted, eventually reaching the rank of General in 1830. He served on several secret missions during the Napoleonic Wars and was wounded in Corsica; in 1826-1828 he commanded the British forces in Portugal. In addition to his military career, William Henry Clinton served in the House of Commons and made extensive improvements to his manor of Cokenach. He sought several colonial governorships unsuccessfully during his career, but was forced to decline the governorship of Malta in 1830 due to ill-health. William Henry Clinton married Lady Dorothea Holroyd in 1797; the couple had two sons and four daughters. He died at Cokenach, Hertfordshire, England, on February 16, 1846.
Sir Henry Clinton, 1771-1829
Sir Henry Clinton was the younger son of General Sir Henry Clinton (1730-1795). He joined the British Army in 1787 and took part in the Napoleonic Wars, eventually rising to command the Sixth Division in Spain in 1811. Clinton journeyed to England briefly in 1813 to convalesce from an unidentified illness, but returned to Spain to lead his forces in the battles of the Nive, Orthez, and Toulouse. He took command of the Third Division at the battle of Waterloo, and led a division during the occupation of France. In addition to his military career, Clinton was a member of Parliament from 1808 until 1818, working in the interests of his cousin the Duke of Newcastle. Sir Henry Clinton's health deteriorated rapidly after the death of his wife Susan (Charteris) in 1817, and he is said to have become a recluse. He died at Ashley Clinton, Hampshire, England, in 1829.
Scope and Contents
The Clinton Papers contain correspondence, letterbooks, financial papers and other material documenting aspects of the lives and military careers of Sir William Henry Clinton (1769-1846) and his brother Sir Henry Clinton (1771-1829). They include hundreds of letters from Henry to William Henry, many written from Spain during the Napoleonic Wars, as well as letters by other members of the Clinton family; journals kept by Sir Henry Clinton, letterbooks of Sir William Henry Clinton, and account books kept by both brothers; bills and receipts; and family papers.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1754-1829; II. Account Books and Journals, 1762-1871; III. Bills and Receipts, 1767-1830; IV. Other Papers, 1769-1879.
Brothers -- Great Britain; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Great Britain -- History, Military -- 19th century; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1800-1837; Account books; Diaries; Letter books; Receipts (financial records); Clinton, Henry, 1771-1829; Clinton, William Henry, Sir, 1769-1846; Clinton family; Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, Duke of, 1769-1852; Great Britain. Army
- Correspondence, 1754-1829, undated; Series I; 3.34; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Chronologically arranged; three folders of family correspondence are located at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains chronologically arranged correspondence from and to members of the Clinton family, principally Sir William Henry Clinton (1769-1846) and Sir Henry Clinton (1771-1829), documenting aspects of their lives and military careers. There are over 800 letters from Sir Henry to his brother Sir William Henry, written between 1811 and 1828, which provide detailed accounts of Sir Henry's military service and of his political activities during his years in Parliament.
  Sir William Henry Clinton's own service during the 1826-1828 campaign in Portugal is also documented in his letters to Sir Henry Clinton from the period, as well as in letters received by him from many correspondents, including other army officers. Other correspondents include political colleagues, members of the British aristocracy, and members of Clinton's extended family.
  - Correspondence, 1754-1766 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1767; 2 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1768-1770 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1770-1778 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1779-1788 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1789-1798 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1799 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1801 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1803 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1805 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1807 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1808; 2 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1811-1812 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1812; 3 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1813 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1814; 3 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1815; 9 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1816 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1817; 4 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1818; 6 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1819; 3 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1820; 13 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1820; 4 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1821; 17 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1822; 15 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1823; 17 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1824; 17 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1824 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1825; 19 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1826; 6 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1826; 13 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1827; 12 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1828; 11 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1829; 2 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1829, undated; 7 (Box 10)
  - Baddeley-Dixon letters, 1777-1807 (Box 10)
  - Maria Augusta and Louisa H. Clinton letters, 1809-1812 (Box 10)
  - William Henry Clinton's children's letters, 1809-1816 (Box 10)
- Account Books and Journals, 1762-1871; Series II; 6.67; (19 boxes)
  Alphabetically arranged by author and then by type of material.
  Series II contains account books, journals and other bound manuscripts written or owned by members of the Clinton family. The series includes an extensive set of Sir Henry Clinton's journals, beginning in 1791 and continuing until the year of his death, as well as a set of account books covering most of his adult life. Also present are letterbooks kept by Sir William Henry Clinton from 1828 onward and three boxes of his account books; notebooks and journals kept by several women relatives; and a notebook containing "Directions for Battalion Guns."
  - Carter, Elizabeth
    - Account books, 1790-1817; 2 (Box 11)
  - Chester, Ann Maria Mary
    - Music books, 1821 August 23 (Box 11)
  - Clinton, "Monsieur"
    - Account books, undated (Box 12)
  - Clinton, Frederick
    - Journals, 1841-1866; 2 (Box 12)
    - Military notebook, undated (Box 12)
  - Clinton, Harriet Carter
    - Journals, 1764-1828 (Box 12)
  - Clinton, Henry, Sir, 1738-1795
    - Account books, 1766-1769; 2 (Box 12)
    - Daily calendars, 1762 (Box 12)
    - Daily calendars, 1763-1795; 3 (Box 13)
  - Clinton, Henry, Sir, 1771-1829
    - Account books, 1795-1825; 5 (Box 14)
    - Account books, 1804-1847; 13 (Box 15)
    - Journals, 1791-1797; 9 (Box 16)
    - Journals, 1798-1805; 10 (Box 17)
    - Journals, 1805-1812; 11 (Box 18)
    - Journals, 1812-1817; 14 (Box 19)
    - Journals, 1825-1829 (Box 20)
    - Military notebook, undated (Box 20)
    - notebook, 1814, undated; 3 (Box 20)
    - Reading extracts, 1805, undated; 2 (Box 20)
    - Record of letters, 1825-1829; 2 (Box 20)
  - Clinton, William Henry, Sir, 1769-1846
    - Account books, 1788-1829; 7 (Box 21)
    - Account books, 1804-1831; 3 (Box 22)
    - Account books, 1833-1846; 2 (Box 23)
    - Day book, 1831-1851 (Box 24)
    - Letter books, 1828-1840 (Box 24)
    - Letter books, 1841-1844 (Box 25)
    - Letter books, 1844-1845 (Box 26)
    - Register, 1800-1834 (Box 27)
  - Dawkins, Augusta
    - "Manuscript of Readings and Thoughts", 1840-1871 (Box 28)
    - Notebook, 1827-1864 (Box 28)
  - Holroyd, Mrs.
    - Account books, 1778-1792 (Box 28)
  - Holroyd, Sarah Martha
    - Journals, 1808-1818 (Box 28)
    - Verses, 1793-1817; 5 (Box 28)
  - Munro, Gordon
    - Account books, 1827-1828; 3 (Box 29)
  - Proby, Susan
    - Prayer book, 1802 (Box 29)
  - Unidentified Authors
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 29)
    - "Directions for Battalion Guns", undated (Box 29)
    - Notebook (school memory exercises), undated (Box 29)
    - Serena, 1794-1850, undated (Box 29)
- Bills and Receipts, 1767-1830; Series III; 2.71; (7 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Series III, Bills and Receipts, consists of seven boxes of unsorted bills and receipts, many pertaining to the personal expenses of Sir Henry Clinton (1771-1829). There are also a number of bills and receipts documenting the financial affairs of his father, General Sir Henry Clinton (1730-1795).
  Oversize bills and receipts are stored in Oversize.
  - Bills and receipts, 1767-1793; 17 (Box 30)
  - Bills and receipts, 1768-1819; 16 (Box 31)
  - Bills and receipts, 1772-1799; 14 (Box 32)
  - Bills and receipts, 1772-1814; 7 (Box 33)
  - Bills and receipts, 1767-1830; 10 (Box 34)
  - Bills and receipts, 1786-1829; 11 (Box 35)
  - Bills and receipts, 1786-1830; 16 (Box 36)
- Other Papers, 1769-1879; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged in two subseries: Artwork and Manuscripts.
  Series IV, Other Papers, contains artwork and miscellaneous manuscripts pertaining to members of the Clinton family. The subseries Artwork includes cutouts of zombies and anonymous portraits, mostly printed, of various persons. Manuscripts consists primarily of school exercises and other papers relating to younger members of the extended Clinton family.
  - Artwork
    - "Drawings and Paintings", undated (Box 37)
    - "Pictures of Gravestones and Portland Place", 1773-1879 (Box 37)
    - Satirical playing cards (partial deck), undated (Box 37)
    - "Zombie Cutouts", undated (Box 37)
    - "Unknowns", undated (Box 37)
    - Clinton, Lou and Sir William Jones, undated (Box 37)
    - J. M. D., undated (Box 37)
    - Dashwood, Charlotte, undated (Box 37)
    - Dawkins Jr., Augusta, undated (Box 37)
    - Fanshawe, Catharine, undated (Box 37)
    - Holroyd, George, 1815 (Box 37)
    - Holroyd, John Baker and Lord Sheffield, undated (Box 37)
    - M. K., undated (Box 37)
    - Marshall, Catharine, undated (Box 37)
    - Montagu, Mary Wortley, undated (Box 37)
    - W. R., undated (Box 37)
    - Stanley, John, undated (Box 37)
  - Manuscripts
    - Letters and essays, 1791-1820 (Box 37)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1812, undated; 2 (Box 37)
    - School exercises, undated; 2 (Box 37)
    - Printed material, 1805-1868, undated; 2 (Box 37)
    - Dawkins, Augusta - Miscellaneous, 1832-1859, undated; 2 (Box 37)
    - Dawkins, F. - Service Record and Other Documents, undated (Box 38)
    - Holroyd and Kennicott - Thermometer, undated (Box 38)
    - Holroyd Clinton, Louisa D. - Essays, etc, 1803, undated; 2 (Box 38)
    - Holroyd, Maria Joseph - School Exercises, after 1813 (Box 38)
    - Holroyd, Maria Joseph - Phalaris of Agrigentum, after 1803 (Box 38)
    - Montagu, Mary Wortley - Theme of the Mouse and Other Notes, 1835, undated (Box 38)
    - Stanley Daughters' - Plays and Poems, 1810-1818, undated; 2 (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous, 1769-1800, undated; 7 (Box 38)
- Oversize, 1765-1840; 2.75; (3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1807 August 22 (Box 39 (Oversize))
  - Bills and receipts, circa 1765-circa 1830, undated; 6 (Box 39 (Oversize))
  - Bills and receipts, circa 1765-circa 1830, undated; 8 (Box 40 (Oversize))
  - Bills and receipts, circa 1765-circa 1830, undated; 12 (Box 41 (Oversize))
  - Drawings, undated (Box 41 (Oversize))
  - Painting, undated (Box 41 (Oversize))